the most random specific topic but I think it's actually kind of cool there's so much to dig into
this just a few quick things we'll do a quick intro I just want to set the expectations for
what we can do in the next hour so the only difference between me and you is I just spend
more time and that's basically it right so I'm not the the big expert that has all the answers you
know if we do I've loaded this all to GPT and then we can ask together and then discover together so
that's where I come I just spent a lot more time trying to understand this my hope is you bring
in maybe because of your background you maybe understand very specific aspects of these in
different ways maybe you see different applications in the way in the work that you do so that's kind
of the the baseline one sec so quick intro I'm proud of I've been gosh I've been interested in AI since
like the NLP days if I tell somebody what NLP now is I don't think they'll understand oh NLP like
what is that right but ten years ago that's where I started a lot of my explorations I'm primarily an
engineering and startup guy right now I actually spend a lot of my time training young people for
like ten months how to do cool things with AI I'm also another professor at UBC so I teach the first
year UBC engineering class so if anyone comes into UBC engineering I'm the first face that welcomes
and into the engineering experiences let's talk about me so what we'll do is we'll go yeah have you have you go to
my class what so funny right after this I teach a dance class at Paz out 8:30 so so if you ever do salsa
dancing or put that up okay so we have quite a few people so we'll keep it short but I still want to hear
from you so here's what I'm looking for name your AI readiness so what I so for me it is number one is
you use chat GPT 10 is you spend a lot of your time understanding research papers digging in and
whatnot and I'm just looking to understand how much like have you dug under the hood so I do use GPT or
we spent some time understanding what is this transformer thing can be cash thing vector thing I just want to
understand how are we feeling under the hood according to that I will real time adjust how
we guide our discussion today cool hi everybody I'm Farah Hussain and in terms of my ranking on that
scale I think I'm somewhere at three okay awesome perfect great hey I'm Molan I would say I'm at five
probably okay actually maybe a little bit of I want to go into like your whole background what you do
too much detail maybe as short as you can keep it whatever you think is important to know as it
relates to this conversation okay so I think in short don't want to be left behind that's fine okay
that's a good that's a good answer that's what she was hoping for good okay so yeah my name is mean I'm
developer so I would say like 80% or eight okay for using the AI stuff so four more as well
I'm Thomas I'd say like four to six somewhere in that range and I'm just like trying to get back into
computer science something awesome I mean I'll say like a free I think I mean I'm just like
trying to get you trying to get to like know more about the AI stuff cool cool okay if he's three I'm two two okay
yeah don't don't hurt him like that how dare you say that you should have heard what he was talking about
but I want to know what's interesting for me is when I get into a case I want to know when to come to the algorithms and try to figure things out I don't need to know them but I need to know
that's what I want to know what my name is Noah and I said about a seven I spent a lot of time when I was
with Pranav last year taking into the transformer and the architecture I'm Zen I also spent a lot of time
with Pranav I would say I'm about six he's going into computer science I'm going to engineer so a little less focus on AI but yeah cool okay
sorry just before you go have you applied a lot of this in your in your work like day-to-day as well okay
very interesting okay just making notes yes my name is Cyrus I say I'm of war but I came here to like catch myself back up to what is currently happening
okay okay
my name is Rachel if you're a Florida I'm probably like a two in a half
but it's the same reason I've been on it
local scale
we're going to normalize this now
you got to rotate them
yeah exactly
yes
I think I'm maybe a two
what is this
cool
we'll catch you at some point so
we'll catch you at some point
I'm sure all of us know we can
represent this as x y and z and
this is a vector it's a line pointing
the direction right GPT we're
working with many dimensions many
many many many many many dimensions
so we're just kind of simplifying it
to this one right the second thing
to understand is dot product very
very important the simplest way I
like to think about dot product is
how similar are two concepts right
that's basically it if I have a
concept a and I have a concept b
how similar are they right so if
they're kind of here they're similar
if they're here maybe not as you
know not not similar at all right
again hyper simplifying this is a
lot more complex but whenever you
hear dot product or things like
cosine similarity things like that
it's just like how similar are they
I think it's just that it's just
the mental model to use
we're pointing out cosign if they
were exactly the same cosign but
what the angles you want
yes exactly one you know we have
yes so it goes one if it's 90 zero
but no correlation so far you know
yeah exactly so and then we have
this concept vector embedding the
simplest way to put it is when we
have text objects can be a lot of
different things if we have text we
put them through an embedding model and
we represent that text as these
vectors right so gp doesn't really
understand English it all just
understands big matrix this road so
that's what we do we take these
objects and we figure out some ways to
make them into these embeddings of
course we're not going to go into the
very specifics it's a whole you know
tokenization all those we don't want
to get into but that's just the basics
nice yeah it's just so clean to
understand and then we have I just
want to show you this video one of my
favorite youtubers on the planet is
three blue one brown he was the guy
that helped me understand what the heck
kqv and like just like understanding
how the key in the query the values all
come together in these big tabla
formats so what I want to do is just
play that first bit so we can better
understand just what these
similarities mean so how does it go
from a sentence to this it's like
23 20 or 30 seconds but just highly
recommend this channel so good the
first step in a transformer is to
associate each token with a high
dimensional vector what we call its
embedding now the most important
idea I want you to have in mind is how
directions in this high dimensional
space of all possible embeddings
can correspond with semantic meaning
in the last chapter we saw an
example for how direction can
correspond to gender in the sense
that adding a certain step in this
space can take you from the embedding
of a masculine noun to the embedding
of the corresponding feminine noun
that's just one example you could
imagine how many other directions in
this high dimensional space could
correspond to numerous other aspects
of a words meaning the aim of a
transformer is to progressively adjust
these embeddings so that they don't
merely encode an individual word but
instead they make in some much much
richer contextual meaning I should say
upfront that a lot of people find the
attention mechanism this key piece in a
transformer we'll get to attention
mechanism in a second but I hope we
understood that it's like we're taking
these words and just representing them in
this n dimensional space I don't know
about you guys but that's just so
freaking interesting like the fact that
I don't know if you guys see this video
like if you take if you take king and
remove something like if you take king
and then add them as a feminine piece
you'll see the vector changes so that
it actually represents queen I'm like
that's it's crazy that all of that is
just math right and this is why I'm
like I if I think about application layer
exploration and I think research expert
this is so much more interesting like
there's so much to dig into and
understand artistically like how all
this comes about so that is just to get
a sense of okay if it's in a
particular direction there is there is
a meaning and semantic attachment cool
the next thing is to understand this
thing called attention again if I would
explain this super super simply we have
our input text it's tokenized means
it's flipped into these individual
components and it goes through our GPT
transformer and then has it open so
that's kind of how GPT just
fundamentally works but if I would ask
what is attention it I kind of I just
put this is like the one line so it is
taking information from past tokens and
helping it inform the current token so
we can figure out what the next one is and
this again the simplest we don't
understand that is you know the more it
allows me to understand in a particular
sentence of what pieces of information
do I need to consider now so I could
figure out predictably what is the next
token going to be right so if I have
more attention layers as you know that
there's a bunch of attention layers
that just simply means it's spending
more time thinking about it right and
then updates the vectors so all this is
like still a little bit confusing I think
the basic thing to remember is
attention is how tokens relate to each
other so understands what the previous
information and packs more context into
the current one right cool just in case
I remember now there's one amazing
character called attention is all you need
yes so I mean attention is all you need is the birth
it's the birth of this all of this right and
I highly highly recommend it literally I
mean it is it is where all this comes
from right have you ever done and
attention is all you know like old
school I have a long time have you done
have you done a reading group on
yeah I think the industry was going in this
direction like it would have happened at
some point yeah okay I just want to pause
here any quick questions does the again the
goal is not to get the details imagine we
have a watercolor painting that's all I'm
looking for I'm not looking for branches
in the leaves in your understanding of
this yet but so far are we good any
questions okay cool okay and then we have
this thing called kidney cash that's
going to come up a little that's
basically the the crux of this paper
right and the way I just think about it
very simply is you know this attention
mechanism spends a lot of time looking
at previous tokens and words to inform
what has to come next so instead of
writing this every time and processing
it every time it just keeps a cache of
all the different keeps a cache and the
best way to think about it is this
information about past tokens and it
just remembers that so you can imagine
if we work with really big really big
vectors and sizes that cache gets really
really big and so this entire paper
today is how do we basically quantize
it and that's the that's the fundamental
understanding it's like a very big
conversation history yes I think I
started using GPT in one chat way too
long and then it starts to slow down
rapidly right and it's just so much
context yes one small aspect of it is
that yes and this is going really really
large so quadratic okay I like searched it
up because I was like what is the KB
cache before this and like AP cash is a
key value capital but then doesn't that
mean that it's like a hash map because
it's a key value pair and wouldn't that
mean that it's like always in constant
time or like why is it why does it get
slower the more that it gets if a key
value pair you can just do like this in
the hash map and it's supposed to be
constant time I mean I my understanding
this is that it just adds to the
computation speed like if you have like
KB caches is added part of the
vector so if you keep if you have to
constantly your attention mechanisms
go back that is actually quite a bit
to process right so that's kind of my
understanding it unless anyone else has
it's also because let's say you never
write the same things attention is all you need
so if you on each iteration of each word
you're trying to understand you go back
to the first word you need to do the
first the second the third the fourth
and the fifth with cache you have cache
storage is the first part you don't need to do
one so it's pretty much but is that
yeah is that what you're asking but
yeah did you understand what KB cache
meant or we're just asking why is it so
big and ballooned down like why does it
slow down
why does it get bigger I mean
go over go over please
I was gonna say I think this whole paper
talks about the efficiency of scoring the KB cache data
in the fine item model hardware memory on your GPU
so if you have an NVIDIA graphics card
like a 5000 you know or a blackbook you know
blackbook GPU plugged inside your computer
it has 8 gigabytes of EDR5 memory
so it comes down to how much data
how can you efficiently tram into that memory
right so in order to keep your AI working
as quickly as fast as possible
we're going to talk about that in so much step today
yeah that's the point of this
if I read it correctly if I understand the point correctly
you know tell them occasionally compress that data
with the KB cache information
so that as much as possible
can be loaded in memory
relatively losses
yeah
okay
but doesn't it conceptually mean
the more
the longer it gets
let's say sentence versus paragraph versus
we need more information to
maintain the semantics of that
what's important
yeah
so that's
isn't that why
it's more important
it's more because of memory
yeah right
so KB cache
these things
are stored in memory
and a lot of the memory is like
I need to access it fast
but memory can't
you guys know like
the simplest analogies like the RAM and storage right
yeah
and then your RAM has like
like it's it's it's to get quick
it's to it's to be able to do quick operations
in nanoseconds
yeah
memory access
for work with a byte of data
exactly
so KB cache
if you if it keeps growing
the memory gets full
and then it just
the latency starts to crash
the things start to crash
so I would say that's one of the bottlenecks
it's because memory is only limited
so the storage which is different
and then there's memory
and that's one of the reasons why
memory chips are gone after price
because as they build out more and more
of these AI data centers
yeah
they're buying
the manufacturers are
switching their
DRAM
their production
from DRAM
to this high bandwidth memory
and so when you go to the computer store
to buy memory
it's in short supply
right
because
all of that
all the manufacturers
like light from technologies
are
making this high speed memory
for all the AI data centers
right
so
all this one
right
yeah
that's insane
and it hasn't changed
in the last
five years
it's like double
yeah
kind of messing with the video
a few years ago
yeah
you can afford it
if you bought it
oh
so look at that
prices for
the kids have surged
yeah
this is interesting
so it has surged
three to four times
there are early 2025 lows
so between
early 2025 and now
it surged three to four times
so
this is precisely why
yeah
i have a buddy
he was buying RAM
with his bold mix
and he had some good products
and he used to sell it
yeah
the reason is because
the manufacturers of
Samsung
have switched their production
from DRAM
which is used in these computers
to HPM
oh yeah
we're going to talk about that too
that's HPM
yeah
like companies
SanGIS
you know
light drop technologies
they said switch
we're going to make the chips
that has the most possible
and that's AI
your ideas
yeah
oh this is good
this is actually perfect
because we're going to get
right into it
I guess literally
this is
basically setting up
what you asked
which is
this grows so quickly
that the
um
man it just like requires
so many more computations
and we just need to find a way
to make this cheaper
and not lose accuracy
so
that's how
that's how we're going to
slowly start to get into this
so if you have your papers
let's work it out
let's get into this
okay
actually you know what
give me a story
what it's been
yeah let's spend some time
I love
oh my god
I spent so much time
really understanding
Shannon's source point
but you want to spend
just one or two minutes
what do you understand
so what I was thinking
about
you said 1980s
way back in the stone ages
in the 1980s
you did a punch cut
because I remember university
they had to get
my first year we did punch cuts
don't go there man
so the Shannon theory
no problem
the way that it was explained to me
the Shannon theory was written in the 1920s
and it had to do with how do you encode information
right
as efficient
with maximum efficiency
so the basic idea was
let's say you have somebody
using something similar to Morse code
right
how fast can you transmit information
over a pair of proper wires
using
how can you encode your information
letters of the alphabet
as efficiently as possible
to transmit as much information as possible
over an OG communication channel
right
that was the basic premise
of the Shannon theory
yeah
it is about information and coding
right
and you guys have
so if you watch the video that I sent across
the example that I love that it gave is
if you have two text files
one text file
is a file just with the letter A
and you have another text file
that is a bunch of random ones
the first text file is going to be 7MB
you can get it down to a few
you know
the other one
the latter one
not as much
yes
and the primary reason why is
AAA
it's predictable
the more predictable it is
the easier it is to compress something
right
and the less predictable it is
the same
and the same
yeah
right
and that's what the sound is doing
and that's actually
how much information can you put
it will also minimize the size
yeah
so the fact that we
you know
that page bullet
letter A
is one big symbol
yeah
so there's
oh god
there's so much we can
now
now realizing what
Sam was saying
yeah
in the last reading group
only spent half the research
like we were filming it through half
so we could see
yeah
so many interesting things here
so
okay
so there's a lot of math
and a lot to peruse through
so
perhaps the way we want to get through this is
you'll notice I highlighted a few things like mean square are a huge component of that today we'll get into it
but the if I would explain turboquant in two to three like sentences
what you're basically doing is you're trying to find to get these you're trying to get these vectors and we're trying to quantize them
and so what we're going to go through today is okay how do they actually do that
there's this rotation piece there is residual piece we'll kind of piece together what all those components are
but what's interesting about this paper is it it takes it's like it takes together two concepts from what's already been done before
so this one big quantized scale of transform method was there before and they're actually introducing that as a way to make sure that all the things get lost in our compression
we have some way to bring that back also that so we'll go into a lot of detail don't worry about too much
but I would say this the the big piece of remember in in this in this first piece as we read this is
yeah we're essentially we're essentially trying to reduce them but the two ways that we figure out okay how good or how effective this compression has been
is to these two things called mean square error and inner product errors okay
does anyone got a sense or have a sense of going to explain or they're going through themselves like what what really a mean square is
has anyone had a chance to have a look into that
want to give it a shot
yeah but intuitively do we have a sense of what that means
I just intuitively what is like a mean square
yeah when I get a shot yeah
like I don't like in stats because I'm thinking 80 stats right now like when you do linear regression the mean squared error it's like because you want to square it because you have on top of the line or on the bottom of the line so it's just a regularized version of adding up all the error
yeah and I think of yeah if something has a really high mean square error that means our original vector and our depressed vector are kind of not similar right and this is analogy of the face and the blurry faces you put it together how similar are they and each
would tell us how similar or dissimilar they are. Anyone thought that's in a part? Let me give it a shot. Okay, so we'll go into it in a little more detail. The whole paper is about these two things, so we'll come to it at some point. I just wonder if anyone had some early ideas on that.
So this actually now comes to answer your question here. So as LM capabilities depend heavily on their model and size of context length, serving them requires substantial memory demands and increase inference latency. And this is what you're talking about, HBM. I highlighted this because I wanted to go down a whole rabbit hole, but I just didn't have time.
Well, that was the whole point, was how, you know, just the most, the most difficult thing to store as much, maybe, pairs in the RAM patch if you have a finite amount of memory. Hardware memory, right? You know, like your NVIDIA GPU, you can buy from, you know, 10 or 12 gigabytes. That's it.
That's it. You want to stop as much data in there as possible. Right?
Yeah, so, so what we're trying to do is, can we try to compress this while preserving the inner product? So the way that I would think about preserving the inner product is what MSC is trying to do is like, hey, are we, can we take this vector and when we compress it,
kind of how, how, how, how similarly. Um, but inner products, I actually had a, I actually did an aerial.
So inner products that are measures how much the similarities between, uh, the vector changes have the compression, and with means better,
it's just understanding, okay, if a higher MSC means the compressed vector change a lot more than the original,
and a lower MSC just means it's taking closer to the original. Um, so I would kind of think about this as distortion, so high MSC means,
it's just, uh, has moved quite a bit more MSC means closer to the original. So I'd keep these two in mind,
because this is what we'll kind of look at throughout the entire as we keep going. Um, okay. Any other thoughts or comments if we keep going?
Yeah, MSC and inner product are related, because A minus B squared, if you open it up, there is B and it's R.
Yes, A minus 2AB, yes.
So then you have to put some levels of equivalence.
At some point, I have the whole math right now, 'cause it's like, we have to get into the math, so, um, we will get into that.
Okay. Uh, I actually wanted to read this part out. So these models must store key value embeddings from previously generated tokens
in the KB cache. We've just talked about that, so you have some context now.
The size of which scales with model size. So if we have bigger models, that means more attention heads.
More attention heads means higher KB cache head. Uh, scaling is a significant bottleneck in terms of memory usage
of computational speed. Therefore, reducing the KB cache. I just look at repetition of why this is important.
Again and again and again. Uh, additionally...
I mean, it's very effective. Any, any improvement in this? Like, you're improving the whole world.
Because everyone is, like, using all these LLs. To improve, like, 5% means you're reducing 5% for everyone in the world.
Because KB cache is very fundamental. So the impact is huge.
Yeah, any progress in others?
Yeah, I can't wait to get to the implementation of this stuff. Because that's where this stuff gets a little more difficult.
Uh, because we're still in theory land, right? We're still, like, theoretically assessing what this looks like.
We'll get to the implementation in a second and see, okay, to what extent...
There's actually some experiments here at the end that shows, okay, how much will we actually able to get a meaningful improvement in these models?
Uh, or improvement in being able to get the right information with the compression, right?
Um, okay, uh, I wanted to highlight this.
"Additional nearest neighbor search in high-dimensional spaces for inner product and cosine similarity is according to shown in vector databases."
Uh, this is basically what I showed you earlier in that video.
Which is, if you want to do search, understanding the inner product and cosine similarity of those two vectors is how we understand...
This is, like, how we pull stuff from vector databases.
So we're still in this early, like, setting up the stage for the paper.
We're not actually getting into much stuff yet.
This is just, like, why it's important.
Okay, and then we get into the first, kind of, like, summary of what this is, right?
So, it's a two-stage process.
So, first, uh, we develop a vector quantizer with optimal distortion rate in terms of the mean spread error.
If you're like, "What the heck does that mean?"
Don't worry about it, we'll get into it.
Subsequently, we apply a one-bit quantizer to the residual, resulting in an unbiased and low distortion inner product quantizer.
When I read that first, I was like, "I have no idea what that means."
Did any of you feel the same way?
Like, "What?
No idea."
But, we'll get into it.
Um, so, this is good.
This is where we start to explore that first half.
So, this is where they're, kind of, getting into this bit.
Okay, so, how do we do that first quantizing bit?
Uh, before, so, uh, before we add the one that they are on.
So, our MSC optimal quantizer starts by randomly rotating d-dimensional input vectors, observing the key fact that each coordinates in the rotated vectors, and then follows the beta distribution.
And then, uh, they design a Lloyd-Max quantizer for each coordinate by solving continuous kinase problems.
Okay, I feel like, "What does any of that mean?"
Uh, we will, again, get into it, but I just wanted to, like, set up all the things before I have a whole thing on getting into it step by step.
Um, with the related work, we already went through Shannon Semmel work.
Um, how do people understand online versus offline quantization?
Does anyone remember?
How do you understand?
Never heard of it.
So, the way I understood it, and please correct me if anyone else has, you know, spent a lot more time in this, I actually wrote it down here.
So, offline methods, they actually start by understanding the structure of the data before they do the quantization.
Um, online methods do it so a little bit more real-time.
Yeah, so online is, like, uh, the speed is a big factor.
Yes.
Because you need to do it, the offline you can, like, make it sleepy-sleep.
Does it overnight, for example?
Does the structure just have more time for it?
And I'd imagine it gives more accurate information, and that's kind of, like, the trade-off in this, uh, between the online versus offline.
Uh, but what we're working with is primarily, I believe, like, online.
Yeah, because you have to do it real-time.
Exactly.
You're talking to the charge of the team and you want it to be able to compress real-time.
Yes.
Yeah, yeah.
And then there's the last concept.
And this is where we start to get a little bit more technical.
Uh, code books, or product quantization.
Are those concepts?
I guess if you've seen the video, you're a little bit more familiar with what code books are.
Does anyone have a sense?
The colors.
Yeah, the colors.
Yes, yes.
So, you know what?
I'll actually bring that again back in when we do it from front to back versus going into
a deep narrow.
I just want to see if there's anything else we missed before we get into things.
Um, okay, I think we're ready.
We're ready to get into the details a little bit.
But how are we doing so far?
Any questions before we go even deeper?
Because now we're actually going into understanding what is this rotation around this thing?
If it's a sphere, like, we'll go into the details, but anything before we get here?
Alisa, are we having an intuitive understanding?
It doesn't matter if we understand all the details, but intuitively?
Yeah, we're here.
Okay.
So, I actually had it right here.
I need to keep you the help.
Like, okay, how can I understand this step-by-step?
If I take a vector, let's actually go through the process one by one.
Right?
Uh, and then we'll pause at every step and really understand why does that matter?
So, yeah.
So, we start with a vector.
We'll start very simple.
Right?
We have a 1, 0, 0.
And then we apply this 3D rotation.
Um, does anyone know why?
Let's, like, start there.
Like, why do we need to rotate this now?
Yeah, why do we need to rotate this now?
Yeah, why?
Yeah, exactly.
Does anyone have a sense of why we need to rotate this?
Like, why can't we just use this and continue with this initial vector?
Why do we need to rotate this now?
Yeah, it's hard to do compression when you have some spiky vectors in that way.
So, again, my understanding of this, not coming into 10 years of expertise in quantization,
but in the time that I spent, I was like, okay, why do we need to do this?
I was really breaking my head on this.
And I think as I understood it, is if we need to quantize it accurately without losing a lot of its meaning, what we need to be able to do is, it's almost like we are striving at the spot.
across, like, across different dimensions across different dimensions across different dimensions.
So, it's just easier to start to process a lot of information.
Because if we have this here, and we run through the mean square error, this stuff will be really big.
Right? Because this is a spike, if anything's really big, and when you run errors on it, that just gets even more.
Right? So, that's what it's intuition for.
Okay? So, that's what it's intuition for. Okay, we need that rotation, so whatever.
Things in that we can do.
But why specifically do you want to work?
Uh, why specifically do you want to work?
Yes.
Oh, these are random.
Yeah, so, so, yeah, that's a good question. Is it randomized or intentional?
Yeah, it's randomized. Um, if it's intentional, that means then...
There's bias.
Yeah, there's bias. There's gonna be a lot of bias. So, we're adding a random rotation.
Yes.
And this is interesting because, like, if you have one, zero, zero, so then that's a concept.
Yeah.
But if you do that tree rotation, can you explain this concept using other concepts that you know?
That's one of the tree. So, you don't give any concept of uniqueness, right?
That's why this helps with compression. So, you're using other axes to explain the same concept.
Oh, okay.
Versus giving it a unique, you know, spot. Yeah.
So, that's where the compression happens.
Interesting.
Because what I was thinking about is, wait, doesn't it lose meaning after it rotates?
I was like, what?
And then I learned that the rotation happens orthogonally.
So, and I was like, okay, what does that mean in this context?
And the way they explain it is, you can take a map and rotate a map.
Within it, everything still is similarly, like, working with each other.
So, it's still the same thing, where internally, we're only taking one vector.
But if we're looking at the vectors around it and we're rotating it, rotation is happening all across the board.
And so, as a result of that, it still doesn't lose its meaning compared to other vectors around it.
So, that's how I understood.
Because it was a way.
Everyone was moving.
But every, but this random rotation is applied to also other vectors in that.
So, it's like, it's like the whole thing is moving together.
Is how I understood.
Yeah, so I, it still rotates independently.
But the, I would think of this as, it's a, the rotational matrix that we're adding is the same.
But the vector is very different.
But the, for example, the, the instructions of how we're going to rotate is the same.
But for every vector, because of where their vectors are, that individual will look different.
Is, is how, okay.
One more time?
Okay.
So, every time you get a new vector, you get a new vector.
Correct.
So, you'll be rotating with the same randomized R that's coming in.
And every, every, every vector map is subjected to the same randomized R.
That R is similar, but the same for a particular.
Is how I understand.
We can also double check her.
I'll bring up the 15, then.
Yeah.
So, what is the same as the other one?
Oh, I don't know the answer to that.
You, so, you're asking, I'm just trying to say intuitively.
You're asking, does the rotational, the rotation of the matrix, repeat the first one more time?
So, I understand.
Um, right now we're using both, um, the reference that .
Okay.
Yeah.
So, the reason I'm going to answer that yet is because I don't know if, because I can use the word decompression that tells me that, uh, you may have not looked ahead with what's happening with the processes yet.
So, how do we pause that, and once you get the end step, if you're like still that question there, I think it will clarify itself five steps.
But if not, we'll come back to it.
Okay, first one, we can spend forever on this first step.
But this rotation method was already there, apparently.
It wasn't you in this paper.
So, that's come back.
Johnson and the stars.
You know, that's the act one, right?
But this rotation piece is already there.
Yeah, that's the act one, right?
Okay.
But this rotation method was already there, apparently.
It wasn't you in this paper.
So, that's come back.
Johnson and the stars.
Yeah.
No, that's the act one, right?
Right.
But this rotation method was already there, apparently.
It wasn't you in this paper.
So, that's come back.
Johnson and the stars.
You know, that's the act one, right?
All right.
But this rotation piece is like a very common, it's like a, in vector quantization.
It's not like a brand new concept.
Yeah.
Is that what you say?
That was the previous one?
Yeah.
What's it called?
It's a polar point.
Yeah.
Is that what you say?
It's a polar point.
I think that's the previous one.
That was the previous one?
Yeah, the previous one.
What's it called?
It's a polar point.
Did you say polar point?
Polar point.
Yeah.
Oh, it's a polar point.
Oh, polar point.
Okay, okay.
Yes, yes, yes.
So, you're saying, man, I use so much of this.
And I use so much of the quad that every time I go to Google, it can turn on the robot.
Okay.
Yeah, so that's kind of, I noticed that this is actually not a new concept within this table.
Okay, well, that's step one.
So, okay, step two is now very interesting.
And it gets a little bit more narrowly.
So, okay, so we're just on the rotation.
Now we're entering this quantizing section.
Does anyone know why this now quantized version of y is just this number, but in positive and negative?
Does anyone know how they can see that?
Because there's only two bits.
Yeah, exactly.
Or in that case, I'd say, in this case, because the one bit is two --
It's 2.7.
I would say in this particular example, because we're doing a simplified version, it's one bit.
Oh, one bit.
So it's zero and one.
So, okay, so to explain that, when we are quantizing, there's something called a quantizing level.
And the best way to think about that is the number of bits we want to quantize something by.
So one bit is?
It's two, it's two -- it's zero and one, right?
So the way you know the number of bits and how many outcomes is two to the power in.
Okay?
So if we have two bits, that is four.
But each time we add more bits, that, again, goes back to the same problem.
We blow things up again, right?
So we're simplifying this.
We're going to use one bit.
This is zero and one.
One bit.
So it's basically two particular outcomes.
So in this case, we just randomly set.
You know what?
We'll do -- we'll do -- we'll quantize it.
But we'll quantize it just by either plus 0.7 or negative 0.7.
This you can set.
Okay.
So that's not .
No.
And why would you choose 0.7?
And this is where you have -- this also gets into some part of the optimization problem.
Which one do you think?
We'll get to this when we get to the mean square error.
Because that's where it all relates.
So the way you pick this is like, hmm, what's the right number where we can start to figure out,
okay, once we try to quantize this, for example, now 0.6.
So what we're going to do here.
So, okay.
So if you're quantized to 0.7, 0.6 is closer to plus 0.6 -- plus 0.7.
So we add that as 0.7.
Negative 0.5 is closest to negative 0.7.
That's what we have out here.
And again, I would say the intuitive way to understand this is when you quantize something, the way I think about it is we have to latch it onto a grid, a fixed grid.
And again, I think the best way to bring that up is actually this piece over here.
You guys remember this from the video?
Okay.
So the way I personally understood this is when we only have two colors, then everything needs to fit and either sort itself into this or this.
So if you have something that's a bit more orange, it won't go into the green button.
It would go into the orange button, right?
But if we increase that to more bits and then we get to, let's say, 64, that means this kind of green can go closer to this kind of green and we're getting a bit more detail.
So I think about it as like, okay, which color does this need to snap to, right?
Now, when you have a one bit thing, there's only two things to snap to, right?
In this case, it's red and green.
In this case, we decided 0.7 or negative 0.7.
So it needs to snap to something.
And then the thing with signs here is just positive is 1, negative is 0, right?
Okay, I'll pause here.
I'll pause here.
So I'll pause here.
Can you snap to something so that you can unsnap?
But if you unsnap back to the original space, you won't move on.
We're not unsnapping yet.
That's where the residual comes in and we'll talk about that.
Yeah, that's after.
But right now we're not like talking about it.
So once we snap this, of course there's some meaning that's lost, right?
Like I think about this photo.
Once you snap to the red and green, we've lost some meaning, like some meaning.
Like some definition, like we lost that sign.
You know what I mean?
So we lose certain definitions as we do this.
But that's the point of quantizing.
We need to, that's the whole point.
We need to quantize it and that this is the first step to that.
Okay.
Let's go to step three.
And again, if you're not sure, please ask.
If I'm not sure, we'll ask back to you today, right?
Okay.
Well, this is like center of center of center of center of center of center.
Sometimes you can reduce a lot of the size.
And the idea is that, like when you reduce the set of PNG to JPEG, it doesn't look very different to the human eye.
So if you're able to re-quantize it and that's the difference.
Yeah.
And think about the number of colors, right?
So we have RGB.
Or you and I can see the RGB colors, right?
Yeah.
But I guess like beyond that, like 4K, for example.
I don't know if you just know that.
It's like hard to actually, like 4K and under, it's a little hard to-
It's hard to tell.
Yeah.
I think some of the things here are just like, okay, can we quantize it in one bit?
But again, once we do this, we lose a lot of information.
So what do we do with that?
So let me just recap so far.
So number one is we have our vector.
We rotate it in some ways so that the things that are more spiky, we even it out.
So at the end of the day, that reduces the amount of errors that we have.
And number two is we have that big vector and then we need to quantize it.
The way we do that is there's a bunch of numbers.
We need to just quantize it to either this number or this number.
So let's say 0.6.
What is that closest to? 0.7 or negative 0.7?
It's closest to 0.7.
So boom.
That's what that would be.
And that's how we get this vector .
So whenever you see y hat, that means it's basically the course for the quantize paper.
So far, this is the compression as a cheat.
Only decide what quantize it.
You have to cheat and write the contrast.
Yeah.
I mean, to be honest, we haven't even done meaningful compression yet.
Because we've lost a shit ton of information now, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like from this to this, we've lost so much information.
So that's the next problem to solve is what do we do then, right?
Okay.
So that's where residual is.
We compute what we lost.
So how do we compute what we lost?
It's actually very simple.
You just subtract the two vectors.
So we have your y minus y hat.
So that is our residual.
So this is the error that is now in our concussion because we lost this information.
Okay.
That's step three.
So far so good?
Okay.
Step four.
What do we do with the residual?
That's kind of the, we're not getting to .
So the residual is like an error.
Correct.
Compression.
It's like a compression error.
Yes.
It is the, it's just like what was lost.
Yeah, what was lost.
Yeah.
It's just, yeah.
It's just what was lost.
Yeah, yeah.
We'll get into the means, because for example, then the question might be what is the difference
between the residual and the mean spreader, right?
We'll get into that in a second.
Okay.
So the question now is what do we do with this R that we have?
Now this is where it gets a tiny bit more complex.
And I try my best, but how do I simplify this?
Because I have a hard time.
So we'll try our best.
Okay.
So we have our R, finally, our residual.
Negative 0.1 plus 0.2 negative 0.1.
Okay.
So what they say here is we store a tiny sketch.
By the way, there's a 10 steps underneath the step four that I, I matched.
Because it was getting too specific.
But I'll explain it as such as I can.
So I don't know.
Actually, did I have an analogy?
I don't have an analogy.
So the way to understand this particular piece and this tiny sketch is, let's say we have
our face.
Okay.
We took this face that was really clear.
We quantized it.
Now we have a little bit of a blurry face.
So we kind of forgot, okay, how do we now, how do we now bring back information that we
have without blowing it up back again?
So what I would do is I would look at the residual, all the stuff that we lost, and I'm
just going to basically extract some hints from it.
So what that means is, it might be like a line.
Like a tracing.
It might not be the full thing, but it might be like a line.
It might be like a particular, like a feature.
And that's what that, that's what this is basically.
So instead of taking a full R, we just take a bits from it.
And that allows us to better understand, because at the end of the day, what's the point of
all this?
What we're trying to do is, when we have a new vector that's coming in, and we're trying
to do a document search for example, we just want to say, is this kind of similar to this
image?
You don't really need the whole image.
You don't really need the blurry image, but with those lines.
Okay.
So that's what this residual bit does.
You're not including the entire thing, because then there's no point of it.
We're just taking a small aspect of that.
We'll do this.
The residual bit?
Yes.
Maybe I can go more into depth.
It's in 2 bits right now, right?
That means we're only at 4 possibilities.
Is that the expense that you have ever in 4 possibilities?
No, we're still in 2.
So we're still...
Like 0, 0, 0, 1, 1 bit?
Yeah.
No, no, no, no.
We're still in 1 bit.
That's only 0 and 1.
So there's only 2 points, yes.
Right?
Yeah, there's only 2, no, no.
We're still working in...
Oh, I see.
It's still 1 bit, but 1 bit has 2 possibilities.
That's what it is.
I had a...
So you're not starting the error there.
You're starting to...
Even the error itself is starting to be contested.
Correct.
Okay.
Yes.
Actually, let me see.
I had more of the...
That's what it is.
You're just now.
You're starting to...
Even the error itself is starting to be contested.
Correct.
Okay.
Yes.
Actually, let me see.
I had more of the...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So I'll actually get into more of the...
I had it right here.
Okay.
Because it went super into the math.
But it does some really cool things.
Like, for example, I'll explain this one component here.
So what this R does, or the way we get to, finally, what parts of this R they want,
is these are really cool projection techniques.
So where they look at this vector from one point in this space, and they project it from that
with a light shining light.
And they're just understanding.
Is it going with the vector, or opposite the vector?
That's how we get...
Is it from the plus side, or the negative side?
Yeah.
So that's where it comes here.
Pick a couple of random views of the vector.
They're predicting a vector of size 2 into 2.
They're also compressing a number of...
No, no, no.
So this doesn't convert some...
Because that's a representation.
So...
Actually, let me see if I can actually bring that up.
Because I think it's a point to visualize it.
In this paper, it's only given in a really complex map.
And that makes it very difficult.
So let me have to see...
I have...
I actually think I have...
Do I have this complex?
So...
And I think I'm just going to try to explain.
We have this residual vector, but we can't take this whole thing.
Because then...
Yeah.
But we need to have some way of including this loss information...
Back into our compressed quantized version.
So that's the problem we're kind of solving.
So the question is...
How do we get an aspect of this...
Into our original vector?
Because what's the larger purpose?
We're not trying to recreate it so it looks clear.
We're trying to recreate it so that when we have a query vector...
It knows to search for this.
It's like...
I think the best way to explain it is...
If I'm in a room of people...
I don't need to know...
How the guy's nose looks.
Right?
Like...
Just from how tall they are...
Or like...
How tall they are...
Maybe the color of their skin...
I can be like...
Oh, they're in that direction.
And I can go there.
Yeah, and sometimes...
Let's say you have your skin...
And they all have serum numbers...
Yeah.
Sometimes it works to just get a team of last members...
And a serum number...
Yeah.
Uniquely identify...
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
I don't need all the details...
To locate where it is.
I just kind of need to know...
Yeah, the guy's tall...
You know...
Is brown skin...
Has hair like this...
So that's kind of what we're extracting from...
The residual vector, right?
That's a good idea.
Yeah.
That's the only way I can explain...
Oh, okay.
Because again...
What's the main goal we're gonna solve...
Is...
At the end of the day...
We're doing this for search, right?
So we're gonna do a query search...
And then we have to figure out...
Can this query search even locate what's similar?
Not exact.
Similar.
So we could...
So just look something like...
Oh, okay.
That's kinda similar.
That's what we're gonna do with it.
Right?
Do you feel...
Yeah.
Do you feel it's actually...
Smart that it's not looking for the person...
By looking for tallness?
Yeah.
So it's looking around and...
Right.
That's exactly it.
That's...
Tonus is unique.
Yes.
Yeah.
Like I'm looking for tallness.
I don't care...
Yes.
Where they are, what they are...
Exactly.
But at least to find the axes where that's unique.
So if everyone is the same height, then tonus...
No longer...
But if everyone is different height, then you can use tonus.
It needs to figure out something unique.
Exactly.
So now we have an analogy in mind.
Let's try to attempt to go deeper in the map.
So...
What this is doing is...
Imagine this is an R in space.
We pick a random view.
So imagine...
So I'm taking this view and imagine this is shining a light.
Or this is not shining a light.
It's a view.
So what it's doing is...
Oh, if I look at this from this angle...
And I look at it and I project this vector on...
You'll notice that...
Oh, okay.
The only information I need is...
Does the projection of the vector go along with the vector?
Or go away from the vector?
If it goes away from the vector...
That means it's not as similar.
If it goes along with the vector...
That means...
Oh, that's kind of similar.
So I'm now going to go closer to the x.
That's like the...
Again...
This step had 10 sub steps.
And I was going through it and I was like...
Should we go down the sub steps?
And I was like...
No.
It's too much.
It's like the game where it says...
Warmer or closer.
Yeah.
Oh, that's a good one.
That's a good one.
Yeah.
That's exactly it.
But that's enough to find...
Warmer or...
Yes.
But it's not just warmer, right?
We also have...
Our quantized vector.
So we have our quantized vector...
Plus a warmer and colder kind of vibe.
Okay.
And that allows us to be like...
Oh, that's kind of all the information we need...
To even determine that...
Oh, as a queried vector...
I'm similar to that.
Okay.
And that's all we're going to solve for.
We don't want a perfect...
In front of GNM...
We don't want a perfect equation of a photo right here.
So they're actually using it as a 0, 1, 3.
Okay.
So 0 means...
Yeah.
Negative.
Okay.
Means going away from the projection of the vector.
That's what the...
That's what I'm saying...
I didn't want to...
The confusion here is...
Wait, are we reducing this to this?
Not really.
Exactly.
It's not the representation.
It's not the projection of it.
Yes.
All we're seeing is...
When we project something onto this vector...
Yeah.
Does the projection of that vector go along with it?
That's plus...
That's positive.
Or go away?
And that's a negative.
When it goes away...
We're just focused on the projection of it.
Okay.
And this...
One just means with it.
Zero means away from it.
Okay.
This is the actual answer for both of us.
Like the...
The math...
The math of this.
We're not done yet.
Oh.
Oh, that's coming the next step.
Okay.
So then what do we do?
Like, okay, we have this residual bit.
Now what?
Like, how does this...
Like, how does this now...
Like, connect mathematically to...
This...
This quantized version we have.
Okay.
Here we are.
So let's go to step five.
Okay.
So in step five...
We're basically storing...
The 101 and 10.
And you're like, what?
That makes no sense.
Why aren't we storing...
Why aren't we storing this...
Why aren't we storing this exact...
What are we storing...
And the sign...
Right?
You don't know how it's like.
Huh?
Yeah, so like...
You're compressible.
Yeah.
One bit.
You don't want to do...
Exactly.
So...
When we...
One bit.
So...
When we...
In the residual bit...
You don't want to do it...
Exactly.
So...
When we...
In the residual vectors...
We are considering something that's positive...
By the way...
We're not...
Uh...
It doesn't mean we're not including this.
We will soon include it.
Because...
Remember the formula that we were talking about?
Uh...
I'll actually bring it up here.
So...
Y times Q...
I'll actually come into this in a second.
This formula actually breaks into...
For example...
Y...
So...
That means...
Y...
Is equal to...
R...
Plus...
Y-hat...
So...
We actually bring back...
All the different things...
To the substitution...
In a moment...
So...
Step five...
We're just storing...
Because one and zero here are the plus and negative signs...
Same thing here with the plus...
We're just looking for...
Like...
The plus and negative signs...
And...
Because the Y...
So...
Now...
If you're trying to compute similarities...
Let me see if I can bring up...
The...
The map of it...
Because...
What is Y?
So Y is the original...
Y is the original back here?
Yeah...
Y...
Is equal to R...
I'm trying to...
Oh...
Is there a pen here?
Is there a...
Oh my god...
Is there a pen?
Ah...
There must be...
That would be...
That would be perfect...
Yeah...
There's a pen...
Oh...
Guys...
This is good...
Oh...
Let's do this...
Okay...
Awesome...
So...
This is my thought...
I wish I could use this before...
I was trying to do...
Okay...
So...
We know our...
R...
Is equal to...
Y...
Minus Y...
F...
Okay...
So...
If you want to compute...
Similarity...
Um...
So...
We have...
We have to compute...
Y times Q...
T is basically...
Um...
Pardon...
A query vector...
So...
But this Y...
You can replace it with...
Y hat...
Right...
So...
Um...
Y...
I'm like...
Uh...
So...
R plus...
Yeah...
R plus Y hat...
Is equal to Y...
Replace that here...
So...
R plus Y hat...
Times Q...
Okay...
So...
Y times Q...
Is the thing we're doing...
That's the original...
It's the goal...
Yes...
And your approximate...
Um...
And so...
That's the course for...
Uh...
So...
Yeah...
That's the course for...
Uh...
So...
Yeah...
Now we're...
Computing...
Similarity...
Um...
I'm not going to...
Wait a second...
So...
Yeah...
So once we actually...
So once we...
Uh...
Actually open that up...
Oh...
You can see...
We're actually already...
Including...
The visual vector here...
And so when you actually...
Um...
So once you...
Once you have that score...
The final one is...
We're looking at...
Okay...
With our query vector...
If we're now...
Timesing that...
Our...
Um...
Uh...
Course vector...
Which is basically...
What we've quantized...
You realize...
Okay...
It's about a 35%...
Similarity...
Wait...
Um...
Okay...
So...
This...
I just...
Open it up...
Like this...
And that's what we have here...
So...
This is our...
Course score...
Uh...
Yeah...
This is our...
Course score...
So...
And then...
I'll probably pause it...
Because now we're going...
A little bit too deep...
And we'll summarize it...
Sort of like...
It doesn't matter where all the math is...
Uh...
This is our...
Collection...
And this is equal to really similar...
Doesn't make sense, huh?
No...
That's how...
That's how they...
That's how they got...
From Y times 2...
Yeah...
Um...
So...
Now we can check...
Okay...
So...
Really the bottom line...
To all of this...
Is this...
Like if I were to like...
Summarize everything...
Anyone want to ask it?
Yeah...
Okay...
Because...
Step 7...
So 0.35...
It's as fast as slightly long...
Because the original...
It's slightly off...
Oh...
It's a terrible similarity score...
Okay...
With...
Given our vectors...
Yeah...
Um...
But...
Baseline...
If they're like...
No...
I just did not track...
The last 15 minutes...
What happened...
Doesn't matter...
All the entries...
Four sentences...
So...
Really...
We need to know...
Um...
Uh...
So...
Does the query behave...
The same way...
As the error...
In those views...
Uh...
So we talked about...
Okay...
Once we have a query...
And then once we have...
The different views...
We have a vector...
To the R...
The residual vector...
It's like...
Okay...
If...
If it's a higher...
Similarity...
That means...
Yes...
It's higher...
And if it's...
That means...
We have a smaller...
So to summarize...
All this...
You can read that...
So the query...
Is a new vector...
That we're comparing against...
The residual bits...
Are tiny bits...
About what the...
Course vector got wrong...
So the floored image...
Go wrong...
And then we check...
Whether the query...
Lines up...
With those bits...
That's where the similarity comes in...
If it does...
Then we nudge the similarity up...
If not...
We nudge it up...
That's basically...
This whole...
In my job...
Uh...
But we skipped...
So much of the...
Yeah...
I'm actually really curious...
I hope that...
Corrections zero...
Mm-hmm...
All right...
So I must have...
Completed something to get...
Corrections zero...
Oh...
This means...
Maybe that...
We were going...
435...
Yeah...
This...
I don't understand...
I guess for this...
Specific problem...
There was no need to correct...
Yeah...
There was no...
Much...
Yeah...
Very little...
To...
Correct...
Yeah...
In this particular example...
Okay...
I wanna pause here...
That was a lot...
As I mentioned...
This is a very dense...
Mathematical paper...
Yeah...
So if you're like 2 now...
You're like put off...
This doesn't make any sense...
Again...
I just wanna redo this last part...
So that we can really...
Do this all together...
So...
Because you've always...
To maintain similarity...
Yes...
In this new space...
We wanna find all the ways...
Yes...
It's like...
I mean...
At the end of the day...
Once...
The whole point of AI search is...
I have a query vector...
If I've now...
Quantized...
My goal vector...
How do I make sure...
That I can still...
Search for that...
Okay...
And so we wanna monetize it...
Without...
You know...
That's also keeping...
Somewhat of the...
The...
The important parts...
That will allow us...
To identify it...
With that...
Yeah...
It's between...
It's...
Yeah...
I would say...
Between...
If it's one...
That means it's like...
Thank God...
And the similarity is...
Based on that potential...
Right?
Because...
You have a word...
You wanna see how similar...
Other words...
And you wanna maintain that similarity...
And...
Do you think...
Does it matter...
Each time of data...
They are using...
Because...
Oh good question...
Does this change...
You mean like...
From the text...
Or...
I mean...
At the end of the day...
All objects...
Are transferred into tokens...
That are...
So...
I don't know...
If...
This will be different...
When it comes to...
If I'm using text...
Or...
I mean...
At the end of the day...
All objects...
Are transferred into tokens...
That are...
So...
I don't know...
If...
This will be different...
When it comes to...
If I'm using text...
Or...
Something that's not text...
Um...
Yeah...
So...
It depends...
I guess...
Complex...
If I'm using...
Some kind of...
Kind of...
Data types...
You have like...
A better...
New...
Oh...
Yeah...
Possibly...
It depends...
I guess...
Complex...
Yeah...
Like it's...
If it is...
A super...
Complex...
Vector...
Like...
Embedding...
Where it's like...
Everything is...
To...
Compress...
Actually...
I'll let you come to their insights...
In a second...
Yeah...
That actually...
Is a small component of it...
Yeah...
Uh...
There is so much...
Okay...
Because...
I'm sure...
We only...
Have the...
But...
We thought about...
Okay...
You can even include...
Direction...
That's very interesting...
It's like...
I have a blurry picture...
And I have the footnotes...
Yeah...
The footnotes...
That's what it is...
I have the footnotes for...
The things that still describe the picture...
Yeah...
And that footnote...
Is just one bit...
Yeah...
That's...
That's the whole innovation of this...
Right...
That's the visual piece...
So...
So this actually...
Yeah...
This actually is a good...
Because...
Then we went into the experiments...
Of this whole paper...
Right...
And I was like...
Okay...
When we read experiments...
What do we really need to understand?
Like...
What are the questions we have asked...
Before we get into it?
So...
It's like...
Okay...
What's the metric...
Right...
We're gonna check...
What is the...
Improvement meaningful?
Which means...
Were we able to get...
A...
A drastic amount of compression...
And still be successful...
In...
A...
A similarity...
Or like...
Finding the...
The query...
We'll talk about that...
So I'm like...
What's the trade up there?
And then finally...
Ken is actually working the world...
We have actually a very good question...
We have like...
The primary questions...
To any...
Anyone who does...
Like...
AI optimization...
These are like...
Yeah...
Like...
We did a fancy...
Theoretical paper...
Like...
Yeah...
Okay...
So what's the metric being optimized for?
Now let's actually go to the paper...
Um...
Yeah...
I basically skipped all of two...
Because...
Uh...
It's just math...
I tried my best to understand this...
And...
It was a mess...
It makes me...
It gave me a lot of appreciation for people that do this...
Um...
Full time...
And actually I came up with a math...
And here I'm like...
Quad coding...
And I'm like...
Oh man...
The research stuff is so complex...
And there's so much more to do with it...
Yeah...
Like...
And this is when I'm like...
When we look at quad applications...
And we write code...
And we just use agents now...
And I'm like...
Man...
There's research stuff behind this...
It's just insane...
And I have...
So much...
Because I'm always...
I'm a math...
I'm an app for your guy too...
Right?
There's so much more appreciation...
For what happened when we look at...
Right?
We're going to look at...
Okay...
So let's go into our experiments...
Uh...
We looked into...
We actually went through all of this...
By the way...
All of what we talked about...
Was this one paragraph...
In the last 20 minutes...
So if you guys want to just do this now...
So...
To address this bias...
And what the bias basically means...
Is...
When it's quantized as bias...
I'm going to get rid of it...
We propose a solution...
That combines...
Turbo-quant MSc...
With an instance of...
QJL...
Which is the one bit...
You know what we did...
So...
Specifically...
Let...
Q...
MSc...
Be the quantization map...
corresponding to Turbo-quant MSc...
With a bit width...
Of...
D minus one...
So if you're curious about...
What this means...
It means...
We put all the bits...
We...
All the bits that we have...
We focus it on...
The initial part...
Of this quantization...
And the one bit...
That's remaining...
We put it in...
We use the QJL1...
So hence...
We have three minus one...
So it's...
Johnston...
And then...
The quantized...
What's the...
Yeah...
Hold on...
Is there any...
So for...
X...
That is included...
Actually...
I don't want to read that map...
We do this...
For any X...
The visual vector...
Defined as R...
As a small...
You can then apply...
This quantization map...
Which is what we did...
Because the way...
That we talked about...
On the...
The visual vector...
The overall...
This is all...
What we did basically...
But...
You...
They obviously...
It's like a randomized...
The...
It is the...
Oh...
That's the good question...
I would say...
That would be...
Actually...
I'm not sure...
Let's find that information...
So...
Q MSC...
It's like...
You have a query...
Or...
You have a vector...
For MSC...
For PGL...
I actually don't know...
Exactly this...
I think it might be that...
Uh...
What is the map...
On this...
The visual vector...
I think...
This actually might be...
The...
Yeah...
The 0, 1...
Like...
For example...
With this...
The number of bits...
That we put in the code book...
I think...
This might be that...
He's going to do that...
Ah...
Okay...
So...
To just go...
There's the random...
Rotation...
So...
You have a random rotation...
That's a random rotation...
We have a Q...
Which is a quantization...
The grid...
That we talked about...
I think that's what this means...
The quantization map...
On this...
That's what I think...
This means...
And...
It's interesting...
They say...
The vector...
Yeah...
Everything...
So...
Would you expect it to be...
Like...
0, 1...
I think it's a little vector...
Like...
And still...
Anything that is represented...
In that...
Is still...
You have 0...
Something...
That's still a vector...
Yeah...
So the JL...
Is like...
Projecting it...
Using this...
I'm just going to go...
Check this...
But maybe...
I'll come back...
Yeah...
That's what it is...
Even I...
I just...
And it says...
What QJL is doing here...
You have a vector...
In high dimensions...
Yeah...
And QJL...
Yes...
Projecting it...
Into a lower dimensional space...
While preserving distances...
So I did the...
Randomized algorithm...
In computer science...
You've seen...
One of the highest...
I've ever...
Done in my life...
Because...
So...
This is a randomized algorithm...
So it's just a random matrix...
Yeah...
Which is...
Very easy...
Right?
Moving it...
That actually...
What it is called...
So...
It's...
But yeah...
Let's say...
I have a question...
Are they doing this...
For every...
Or...
Just like...
For every token...
That we have in this region...
Or...
Every token...
Yeah...
So...
Actually...
I mean...
This is for...
I would say...
That's a good question...
When does it happen?
Does it happen...
At the end of every...
Attention...
I actually don't know...
Because...
Online...
Right?
Yeah...
So when...
That's a good question...
When does this exactly...
Can you look it up actually?
Let me...
I have it right here...
So...
Actually...
I have it right here...
Uh...
I can...
Oh...
By the way...
I use something called...
Heptabase...
To do all my research paperwork...
Um...
So...
At...
Point...
Yeah...
I don't know...
Here's a question...
At what point...
Is this...
Every prompt...
Right?
Apply...
Uh...
In the mix...
Apply...
Is it...
Yeah...
Um...
Is it...
After...
Every token...
It has to...
Right?
Because...
Every time you have a new token...
Yeah...
That's what I'm thinking...
The similarity changes...
Like...
Everything's...
That's what actually...
We do it...
That's why this is like...
One of the most...
Very nice...
So I asked to follow up here...
It says...
Oh, you already did?
No...
It says...
This is not applied after everything...
So then...
Okay...
Then when is it applied?
We'll give you the next answer...
When is it...
Yes...
When is it applied?
It is applied at the moment you want to compress or approximate vectors...
For example...
During attention...
When storing or retrieving KVCAD...
When approximating inner product...
During modern conventions...
To reduce memory...
Bandwidth...
So...
Okay...
So it's not every token...
But every token...
Yeah...
Every moment...
I mean...
That's the whole point of KVCAD...
Yeah...
So...
Only when you do the query...
It does that...
That actually...
Makes a little bit of sense to me...
And...
That actually...
Subwise...
What it's from...
So...
Every time...
Yeah...
Any word...
Add to the content...
If you need to do...
Does that also mean...
You can...
Everything...
Yeah...
There's a...
You know what...
These are freaking...
Fantastic questions...
Like...
Yeah...
You should...
When does this...
Okay...
Short answer...
Oh...
This one says yes...
Wait...
Let's do this...
Short answer...
Yes...
In autoregressive generation...
The model runs...
The...
The forward...
Passed loop...
And attention...
Step-by-step...
And repeats the process...
Once...
Per generated token...
After selecting...
Okay...
The current token...
Forms a query...
And attends...
It's...
It's only...
Appended...
So...
Because...
If you...
Random...
Direction...
Random location...
The...
Old...
That's actually...
Good point...
Okay...
It's only...
So...
I...
Basically...
No...
I...
I mean...
When...
You...
Apply...
Uh...
When...
You...
So...
When...
You apply...
Uh...
The entire...
Where...
Exactly...
And...
The...
Generation...
Of...
Process...
Is this...
Applied...
To...
The...
So...
Here...
It's giving me...
Something...
It says...
The...
Token...
Embedding...
Then...
Vectors...
And...
Before...
Storing...
Or...
Using...
Those...
Vectors...
It applies...
To...
The...
Vectors...
And...
Then...
Applies...
Okay...
So...
I guess...
The way I understand it is...
Is that...
Um...
Okay...
So...
In a normal way...
It would have to do all of these computations to get to the data cache...
Oh...
Okay...
So...
In a normal way...
Without all of this...
How does it work...
In GPT...
You press the cloud request...
It does a lot of the math...
Um...
Uh...
It does a lot of things...
It's just that...
Next time you put a prompt...
It's just...
Different math...
The GPT...
There's still like...
A bunch of math...
So...
The second you start to query...
It will just like...
It will apply these new rules...
When it processes the GPT...
So...
It makes sense that...
Every time you run...
From your query...
Yeah...
That actually makes sense...
That makes a lot more sense...
Okay...
But not every token...
Every query...
This is how I...
Yeah...
So...
Okay...
The TLDR...
Because we're now super...
Essentially 5...
So...
We didn't even get to the last part...
Um...
Maybe if I were to summarize...
Some interesting things...
I thought the most interesting thing...
In the experiment...
Was actually...
This one...
So...
They ran a lot of other...
Quantization runs...
And this is called...
A needle in the ASAC test...
Where you're looking for...
A very specific...
Hidden sentence...
In a very long...
Uh...
Just...
And they found that...
Oh...
TurboQuant actually had...
The most...
Success...
With it...
Out of like...
The other ones...
I'll try to confess...
Yes...
But...
Here's the...
Here's the controversy...
Here's the key...
In the...
In this industry...
Because...
Um...
Apparently...
When they were doing...
The TurboQuant...
To get better...
TPs...
Uh...
And...
Photoware...
Uh...
And so...
I was like...
Oh...
Wait...
Doesn't that...
Really...
Break the...
Because...
Doesn't it all have to be...
That's why...
Like...
That's a good question...
So...
Okay...
Let me speak about it...
So...
Why is it that...
Uh...
Different DQs...
Um...
I don't know...
That's a good question...
Maybe...
Because one might have...
A bit more...
A bit more memory...
But...
Even then...
Like...
This whole point was...
They were reducing it...
So...
I don't know...
But when I was reading it...
And I was like...
Wow...
They actually use different ones...
And it was the whole thing...
Um...
But...
That's actually one that I looked up after...
Yeah...
That's a good point...
Is um...
One precision between...
Uncompressed...
That's the...
Yeah...
So...
What this says...
It was...
Uh...
So this means...
That...
It was as good as...
An uncompressed model...
Uh...
In finding a very particular sentence...
In a really big attack...
Essentially...
Why was an uncompressed model...
Like...
Is full precision...
The...
Uncompressed model...
So...
It's more so that...
If...
If you're always comparing...
Your relative terms...
You're comparing it to...
It's not that...
The uncompressed one...
Doesn't have loss...
You're just treating that...
As a standard...
So...
That is a standard...
And how far away...
Are you from that...
Does that make sense?
Oh...
Because you're saying...
It's not...
100%...
Yeah...
Because that's also difficult...
And it's getting it...
The exact same...
Yeah...
You know...
So...
It's not able to find a needle...
Even if...
Uncompressed...
So...
How do we understand this?
We're comparing this...
Against...
An uncompressed...
An uncompressed model...
As the performance...
So...
If...
This did...
As well...
As an uncompressed model...
Uncompressed model...
Had to be safe...
But...
If we did...
Exactly as well...
As an uncompressed model...
It would have been 100%...
So...
Which one...
Okay...
So there's no...
I was just wondering...
What...
Oh...
That's another...
That's just another...
I think that's just like...
Another one of those...
Yeah...
It's like you're like...
Full...
You can't get higher than that...
If you get higher than that...
No...
My thing is...
Full position was a different...
Um...
Let's see...
Because you said that...
So...
Yeah...
Full position did it...
Let's go back...
Um...
I feel like the full position...
Is like the one...
Power...
You just want to be more efficient...
Yeah...
Actually...
That's a good one...
I actually don't know...
What the full...
All right...
Where's my data...
Yeah...
It's a little bit slower...
I don't know...
Uh...
What is the full position...
Yeah...
It's a little bit slower...
I don't know...
What is the full position...
Yeah...
I don't know...
It's a little bit slower...
Uh...
What is the full position...
Comparison here...
In the middle...
And the...
Uh...
That...
Yeah...
It is...
If you understand...
I think...
The full position...
Even has...
4X...
That's the...
But what is the full position...
Is that full position...
Like...
Does that mean...
It's...
I don't know...
No compression...
Are you sure?
Yeah...
Is that what full position...
Or is it just the meaning...
Of another...
One of the...
Quantitation...
No...
It's the one that...
There's no compression...
Could be...
Yeah...
Because I want to show like...
Do you want to show the other focal person...
Or the other one...
Okay...
Great...
Good...
Okay...
So then I got mine...
Because I thought...
This is just like another...
So I was like...
Oh okay...
It's just another...
But you're right...
It wouldn't make sense...
Why would they include another one...
And why would they say...
That they were like...
Really about the rest...
So full position is...
As I'm saying...
This is the model's...
Yeah...
Even if it doesn't make captions...
It's the same exact performance...
Uncompressed...
Yeah...
But the uncompressed baseline...
Doesn't say that it's full position...
It's the baseline run with no...
Okay...
So you are correct...
KB cache...
The model evaluated...
That standard quoting point position...
Use as the reference script...
So saying...
So this is basically saying...
It is performing...
Basically...
Exactly as good...
As the full position...
Because...
So this is basically saying it is performing basically exactly as good as the full position.
Because we're encoding things in like one bit versus like 16 bits in a whole.
Okay.
I feel like those are the big things here.
We went a bit into the GPU performance, so that's what we want to bring up real quick.
Right here.
So this was run on the NVIDIA A100, I actually wrote it down here, there was some of the things
that were going on.
But from what I saw in the paper, I'm just going to recall what I remember and understand.
So we evaluated two quantification methods, the method here.
I think from what I understand, they were able to run it on this GPU and we were able to successfully
get the metrics that we talked about here.
And the whole point that, oh, actually this you can actually apply in a GPU, make it work.
And the last question I think that came to my mind and maybe we'll close here is, okay,
what would it take to bring it to the real world?
I don't think we've gone through this.
Like what are the, what do you guys think are the biggest challenges following next?
For those that you actually work on.
Yeah, so, so, so I actually asked this question, I'm curious what you guys just from doing this
so far, if you think from our, like our perspective, what would be the biggest roadblocks in actually
implementing the, like tomorrow for roadblocks specifically?
Yeah, like implementing this QD cache mechanism, what would be the hardest part of this, right?
I think it's convincing, because it's, it's just a random method.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like it turns up into the location as well.
They also have this thing, right?
That, I would say yes.
Yeah, yeah, but, but there's actually a few that, that was actually quite surprising to me.
I asked if the GPT is on my way there.
So anyone else, I want to have guesses before I pull this up?
.
Exactly, yeah.
I have, I can give a comment.
So, yeah.
.
But here's my comment.
Maybe I can give a comment just before I, maybe before I show the answer, yes.
Yeah, so, because here we see like perfect score, but it's not a representation of the real world.
.
I guess the point, I'm almost like, oh, what's like at a harder level?
Maybe this is because we worked, we didn't work with that thing.
I wonder if it's that.
You're the answer that it came out, actually.
So, the way I understood it is that GPUs are structured a particular way to do particular processing
for particular bits.
.
And that's just locked in.
Yeah, that's a good one.
And to redo some of the mathematical architecture for how the GPUs work, to make that happen,
is more difficult.
So, that means the engineering and way we, like the CUDA engineering and where we do it,
needs to change for this to work.
So, I'm like, why not?
I still don't understand.
It says it's operationally output.
And I'm like, okay, I don't understand what that means yet.
It says kernel winds do not automatically become certain winds.
So, what I heard, understand this as is when we're doing inference at that large of a scale,
we might see like localized efficiency.
But when we're doing it at a scale, it might not work.
Yeah, this is the thing.
Yeah, because it shows like maybe in a real world.
Yeah, but sometimes it's like what?
Like what is it about the real world?
I wasn't able to get to that point.
I spent too much time in the math and I was like, oh shit, I forgot a real world understanding.
Like, wait, why can't we do this yet?
Yeah, I think we could spend a lot more time on this.
But I think this is a good time to pause.
How are you feeling?
That was a lot.
A brain's probably not.
I think what I hope, if you don't remember any of this,
I just hope you have a bit more bits in your brain about vectors.
And just how, at least now when you look at AI,
you now have a visual thing of like these vectors moving around to make things happen.
Even though like practically, what will you do with this information?
I don't know how much you would apply it.
Well, we do this a lot in like early go to that target space.
That's where the models are, where the models live.
Right?
They have a lot of front-size versions in many different models.
Yes.
And I'll see this.
And I can put in your computer.
And so they actually did this for the Quinn.
Yeah.
They were--
Oh, wait, what?
Edge computing could become more possible.
Oh, that's a good point.
Yeah, yeah.
When it's for local processing.
Yeah.
So maybe if I were to do this and if I had infinite time,
I would load like a local search model,
like an open source local model.
And I would see if I could like implement this.
Quantize the hell out of this and then that's where--
To maintain information, then--
That's actually a really good point.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Because the way the future's going is more local, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Can you bring these big models and you don't have the brand
in our computer to be able to process all this, so--
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Ooh, you know the other piece that we meant to--
Privacy, they don't have to do the big models.
Yeah, yeah.
The last question is how do we bring agents into this?
Any ideas?
Yeah.
And that's actually where I was like,
"Oh, that's actually very interesting."
Yeah, but how could we use the agents to be more efficient
even in this whole query process?
Has anything come to mind?
Because right now, if you have to search for something,
it's like we're doing a search,
but there isn't much that's happening.
For example, a search isn't just a search.
There's ways you can search for information
so that we're giving AI more.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, but it's just an authentic search, right?
Yes.
You have a lot of context, like emails and all that.
Yeah.
Can you efficiently get the people's most relevant?
Yeah, and have the most--
Google plot to arrive?
Yeah, yeah.
Triple plot to arrive.
Yeah.
Yeah, and have the most accurate plot.
Because to develop the plot,
you're very difficult by the agentic systems
that can understand how things work.
Then we can actually do, like, iteration moves.
Maybe the first one, we're not getting the right answer.
Then agents can learn how do we have the right kind of query
to get the right kind of answer.
Yeah.
So that's, like, the other, like, option.
Ooh, there's actually lots of opportunity
for using agents to make this.
Yeah.
You can contact all the steps to the agent.
Right.
And just give in better--
like, it will help optimize the--
optimize a lot more.
And I thought that was really interesting.
Um, okay.
I think that's a good place to pause.
Any last thoughts or anything else to share
before we close?
This is a very difficult one to do.
I'm not going to lie.
This is--
Yeah.
Do you want to host it?
No.
I--
By the way, you should know.
We--
I have to read it.
You see?
No, I have.
I think you guys should host it.
But by the way, this is just my plug for this book.
It is, like, I'm reading it right now.
And if anyone wants to start to approach AI for parts,
and, like, and just getting really curious about the math,
I love this book.
It goes from--
if you have no knowledge in math,
it will go from zero all the way up to transformers.
And it kind of, like, winds it up so, so wonderfully.
Yeah.
You know, at one point, I'm like, what's that?
And I was asking myself,
should I--
if I have a set amount of time,
do I spend more time in the theory?
Do I spend more time in the application?
Do I spend more time in the coding stuff?
Or do I spend more time in the research aspect?
I'm serious.
How do you think about that?
Because the thing is, like,
when you do the research, like, the theory,
you understand that the limitations of the application.
If you know that things cannot be better than that,
we have no idea.
And now we think about how do we improve model performance.
I'm like, oh.
Yeah, you can do it.
I was like, oh.
There's this thing called KV casting.
I know that's bottleneck.
Yeah.
There's-- if I have a whole new node that didn't know,
how am I going to apply this?
I don't know.
I might want to do my own, like, local model
and see if I can implement this.
But that's going to where my extension is going.
Yeah.
So let's see if I want to obtain it.
I'm going to upload this PDF to a platform.
It's an optimized base and inspired by the algorithm.
Yes.
And that's Codex do it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The last thing I'll say is the next-- the next thing I want
to do, actually.
This is Sekar-- Sekar and I are extremely curious about this.
Is we're both biology nuts.
And our next-- the next topic I'd love to host at some point
is how we can use things like AI to develop mRNA vaccines.
What does that process look like?
Right?
And I was just-- I was just sharing--
I was just sharing before you came.
The-- it's actually not that complicated than most people think.
There's this platform called OpenVax.
You just heard that story about that dog?
Yeah.
On Twitter?
About how this guy was able to create an mRNA vaccine
for his dog using chat GPT and Apple phone.
And, of course, like, in association with some professors,
because he needed professors to formulate the bio.
But he did all that literally just--
Yeah, but to design the mRNA vaccine,
he did not need that.
He just could use that-- use codex.
OK, too.
Yeah.
So would I ever be interested in that?
Like, looking at biology?
Yeah, of course.
Understanding proteins, understanding, you know,
cancer tumors.
And that actually, you know, over this, that is my personal area
of interest.
Like, I'll just show you here.
I spent a lot of time trying to understand, like,
how vaccines are made, and how do we do this?
How do we use the effort?
I think in the next two years, yes, this is one area,
which is, like, AI and agents.
But the next year is the year of biology.
Yeah.
And--
To do this work even better.
That's an enablement.
It's an enablement as well.
So basically, there is a question that the agent--
I mean, that's .
Basically, that when the agent,
the access of the system of the system,
you can use a .
It's basically a .
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Oh, that's actually nice.
I mean, that--
You can get a much better--
Yeah.
That's the idea.
We have some--
I wasn't talking about this.
We have some applications where we don't use--
you have-- you have signaling.
So we want--
but we think of it more as a larger concept.
We don't think of it as a larger concept.
So you're signaling, but what's the objects?
Is this like-- what's the object we're putting on the--
It's just a thing like--
That's the implementation of .
Okay.
Another channel of .
Oh, okay.
Wow.
Awesome.
I loved it.
Guys, that's the thing.
So I don't know if you guys know,
there's no like hierarchy of like who gets--
If you have interesting ideas,
like I want to present this paper.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
It's not like I'm a deep expert,
and I'm like, I'm here to teach.
I just like--
I use this as just an excuse for me to learn,
and then we get to share and learn with each other.
And if you're like, this paper's awesome,
I'd love to discuss this with everybody,
and you can use it as a forcing function to learn yourself,
please message it.
It's a very good forcing function.
Yeah.
Yeah, and then people--
It would be interesting to know what are your roadblocks
in biology.
Oh.
I have infinite pieces.
As part of your paper.
Yeah.
But would this be an interest?
Would--
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So we'll do one, maybe two or four weeks from now.
Sure.
I'll host one of these.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Oh, then we can get bio nerdy.
Yeah.
Oh, that's going to be a difficult one to finish in an hour.
It's so interesting to like biology and chemical reactions.
Anyone here-- you do chemical engineering.
Anyone else-- I know you do--
you guys don't answer the question,
but for anyone else in the bio, just like have a curiosity.
Do you have a bio?
Okay.
I work with Genoves Labs.
Oh, shoot.
You work at Genoves Labs?
Yeah.
We work with Genoves Labs.
You work with Genoves Labs.
I don't know anything about it.
Okay.
Okay, so you build work for solutions for Genoves Labs.
Okay, anyone else do bio stuff or are you interested in--
Okay.
This will be me having you join my bio cult.
I think we need more people into biology.
I think when we were young,
we learned biology was mitochondria is the powerhouse of the cell,
and then that's basically the extent of it.
And I think if we spend more time understanding this--
We can achieve immortality.
Yeah, we can be like Brian Johnson and live forever, right?
Find a way to sequence--
Don't die.
That will end some time.
All right, thanks everybody.
Thank you.
That was so interesting.
Yeah.
Are you working the same time?
What?
No, I just locked the whole meeting, and then using the LLM to translate into the meeting
roll.
How did you go?
What the?
What?
So that's the meeting roll.
Yeah.
What's the transcriber that you used?
Sorry?
Which transcriber did you use?
Do you have like a--
I built my own.
Oh, shit.
What the hell?
So this is the--
You're insane.
It's still prototype.
And then using the LLM to translate into the meeting roll.
How did you go?
What the?
What?
So that's the meeting roll.
Yeah.
What's the transcriber that you used?
Sorry?
Which transcriber did you use?
Do you have like a--
I built my own.
Oh, shit.
What the hell?
It's still prototype.
So--
How did you like to do that?
Uh, so we just recorded the load and then say study.
And then we speak.
And then we transcribe into the--
Into the line transcribe and police transcribe.
And then there's a topic.
Yeah.
So when the guy keeps saying, the percentile keeps saying.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They keep transcribing.
And then I can watch what he's talking about.
And then what's the--
What's the topic about it?
But it's still a prototype.
And I'm still working on it.
Dude, it's fucking insane.
What the--